<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>meta on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in meta on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Yet another blog revamp</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-10-26_yet_another_blog_theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-10-26_yet_another_blog_theme/</guid>
      <description>Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s time to redo my blog again.
This time I found an ultra light-weight blog theme. This page here is under 100KB!
I wanted to make something that acts more like a homepage for my research, rather than a blog. I still have all my blog posts, but now the focus will be on a more professional presentation of my work.
This theme is really what I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted all along: a home page with a max-width for the text, table of contents, and built-in local search!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog update</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-02_update/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-02_update/</guid>
      <description>Brief update on the blog: I had been running a custom fork of the Anatole theme; it diverged pretty heavily, and I found a nice way to customize the CSS. Behold! The new-and-improved blog.
Some of the new extensions to Anatole include the ability to set a static page as your profile; I&amp;rsquo;ll do this and include links to lists of publications and whatnot. This should make my blog a better place for my professional/academic life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comments</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-06-comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 02:55:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-06-comments/</guid>
      <description>I got Disqus working! You&amp;rsquo;ll notice at the bottom of the page is now a place to leave comments.
Disqus has their privacy policy here. They make money through advertising, which is unfortunate, because that means they&amp;rsquo;re selling some of your (and my) data to third parties. That&amp;rsquo;s pretty common these days. :-/
If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to be tracked, you can enable content blockers in Safari by going to Preferences (⌘-,) &amp;gt; Websites &amp;gt; Content Blockers and toggling the blocker:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
