<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>meta on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in meta on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My promise to keep everything original</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-09-23_all_original/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-09-23_all_original/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a strange email the other day. Here it is, with parts redacted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is G&amp;mdash;, I am the main editor at &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While browsing your site, I noticed you have an amazing article from this page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Link to an extremely old post of mine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team actually just published a comprehensive article on &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Semi-related title&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; which I think your visitors would truly
appreciate and add value to your awesome article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check it out here: &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were willing to add our link to that page, I would be more than happy to share it to more than a thousand of our social followers to help you
gain some visibility in exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think and thank you for your consideration!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mail program correctly marked it as spam, which I appreciate. (Besides the spammy feel of the text, the article of mine they reference is an &amp;ldquo;amazing&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;300 word blurb about a one-day project I did in 2017. Sheesh…) I was a little shocked that someone would ask me to engage in the kind of social-metrics-engineering which I feel has contributed directly to many of the social problems plaguing us today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to make a public promise that I would hold myself to. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a scholar. As such, I have a sacred duty to uphold truth at all times and to share knowledge freely. I will never do anything that might compromise my ability to do such. If there is anything beautiful, truthful, or honorable, I will promote it. I will never accept bribery or engage in influence peddling; I find it intellectually and morally repugnant to use my station as an academic for personal gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll make mistakes—and I won&amp;rsquo;t stop talking about tools and services that I think genuinely serve my desires for greater knowledge, understanding, and freedom—but I will never do this in exchange for money, social clout, or whatever. If I attain any fame, it will not be because it was my end goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, G&amp;mdash;, here is what I think of your offer: &lt;em&gt;get lost—your proposal disgusts me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meta: Update should fix RSS feeds</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-05-13_rss_fixup/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-05-13_rss_fixup/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently made an update to how I build my blog. I like writing my posts with Org-mode because it provides a richer markup language than Markdown. Plus, more Emacs = more good. &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; has support for Org files, but there was a problem with the RSS feed generation: all of my posts written in Org got truncated at some point. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if the fault lies with Hugo itself or with some problem in the theme I use—whatever it was, I don&amp;rsquo;t have the time right now to debug that and submit a good bug report or a fix. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/&#34;&gt;ox-hugo&lt;/a&gt; org-mode exporter, so I still can write my posts with Org, but then let Emacs export them to Markdown for Hugo to process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s a Rube Goldberg machine. But what would a programmer&amp;rsquo;s blog be if the build wasn&amp;rsquo;t convoluted like this? Anyway, RSS feeds are fixed now—I checked. If you happened to read anything only via RSS, and found the content cut off at a strange point, this might have fixed it for some posts. Let me know if you run into any other strange issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yet another blog revamp</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-10-26_yet_another_blog_theme/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-10-26_yet_another_blog_theme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s time to redo my blog again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I found an ultra light-weight blog theme. This page here is under 100KB!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make something that acts more like a homepage for my research, rather than a blog. I still have all my blog posts, but now the focus will be on a more professional presentation of my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This theme is really what I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted all along: a home page with a max-width for the text, table of contents, and built-in local search!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog update</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-02_update/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-02_update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Brief update on the blog: I had been running a custom fork of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lxndrblz/anatole&#34;&gt;Anatole&lt;/a&gt; theme; it diverged pretty heavily, and I found a nice way to customize the CSS. Behold! The new-and-improved blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the new extensions to Anatole include the ability to set a static page as your profile; I&amp;rsquo;ll do this and include links to lists of publications and whatnot. This should make my blog a better place for my professional/academic life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have lost my comments and metrics plugins; I&amp;rsquo;m debating about whether or not I will want to re-include them. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t getting too much benefit from them (though it was exciting to see when a post I wrote made it to the front page of HN!) and they&amp;rsquo;re a little bit of a hassle to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I&amp;rsquo;m trying out &lt;a href=&#34;https://sr.ht/~ashton314&#34;&gt;SourceHut&lt;/a&gt; to host some of my projects; stay tuned for a post about μKanren, a tiny logic language that can be embedded into pretty much any language you want. You can read the material that will form the source of my post &lt;a href=&#34;https://git.sr.ht/~ashton314/microKanren&#34;&gt;here on SourceHut&lt;/a&gt; if you are impatient.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comments</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-06-comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 02:55:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-06-comments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got &lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com&#34;&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; working! You&amp;rsquo;ll notice at the bottom of the page is now a place to leave comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disqus has their privacy policy &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.disqus.com/terms-and-policies/disqus-privacy-policy&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. They make money through advertising, which is unfortunate, because that means they&amp;rsquo;re selling some of your (and my) data to third parties. That&amp;rsquo;s pretty common these days. :-/&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; want to be tracked, you can enable content blockers in Safari by going to Preferences (&lt;code&gt;⌘-,&lt;/code&gt;) &amp;gt; Websites &amp;gt; Content Blockers and toggling the blocker:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;kg-card kg-image-card&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/content/images/2019/01/Screen-Shot-2019-01-05-at-19.42.15.png&#34; class=&#34;kg-image&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Enabling content blockers in Safari&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t found a way to enable this in Firefox. Firefox generally does a pretty good job of blocking harmful things—I guess it doesn&amp;rsquo;t consider Disqus &amp;ldquo;harmful&amp;rdquo;. ¯_(ツ)_/¯ I don&amp;rsquo;t ever use Chrome, Opera, Brave, or Edge (I know—big surprise on that last one) so I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to do it there. Let me know if you figure out some privacy measures that you can take with those browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I hope if you want to leave a comment, you&amp;rsquo;ll do it here instead of on Facebook. :) That way I&amp;rsquo;ll see it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
