<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal Blog on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal Blog on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Christmas 2021</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-12-25_christmas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-12-25_christmas/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s my first Christmas being a dad. The end of the school semester was unusually stressful; I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time or energy to anticipate Christmas. But I&amp;rsquo;ve felt a marked lack of eagerness for getting presents. That feeling wanes each year—something I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for—but this year I only felt an eagerness for a time of peace and celebration with my family. Peaceful it has been.
My family isn&amp;rsquo;t perfect. (My baby daughter is about as perfect as they come, though!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reluctance to Bear a Symbol</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-09-19_symbols/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-09-19_symbols/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I feel uncomfortable with many symbols. I might have opinions about a subject, but there&amp;rsquo;s rarely a camp that has some symbol, flag, slogan, etc. that I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with adopting because that camp does not accurately reflect my opinion. All too often, a slogan takes on more than its surface meaning, and that can make using that slogan tricky.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Health and Taking Care of Yourself</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-08-14_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-08-14_health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s going to be another long night. My baby has reached the point where she&amp;rsquo;s too tired to sleep. She alternates between screaming at 90+ decibels and sleeping fitfully. She only transfers from the crying state to the sleep state after prolonged, labored rocking and soothing. She transfers back to the base crying state on her own after a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This Too Shall Pass</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-06-13_this_shall_pass/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-06-13_this_shall_pass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s cliché at this point to say that 2020 was a rough year. I&amp;rsquo;m grateful in that I and my wife were relatively unscathed by the pandemic. I had some personal health issues however that by themselves made 2020 a bit of a struggle. I learned some important lessons.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Easter 2021</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-03-21_easter_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-03-21_easter_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love Easter. In my mind it is just as important as Christmas. Indeed, if Christ had not died for our sins and been resurrected, then there would be no reason to celebrate His birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recorded a short, simple vocal arrangement of &amp;ldquo;O Savior, Thou Who Wearest a Crown&amp;rdquo; by J. S. Bach with my wife.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 11th</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-09-11-september-11th/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Sep 2020 19:58:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-09-11-september-11th/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today is September 11th. I remember waking up 19 years ago, coming into the living room, and my dad getting down on one knee so he was closer to my level. He told me that earlier that morning two airplanes had crashed into some tall buildings in New York City. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what that meant at the time, but I soon found out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quarantine in the 1600s</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-09-05-quarantine-in-1600s/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 17:35:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-09-05-quarantine-in-1600s/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a long six months that we&amp;rsquo;ve been under quarantine and other disease-limiting measures. It hasn&amp;rsquo;t been easy, but thanks to something I saw at 
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K%C3%B6nigstein_Fortress&#34;&gt;Königsstein Fortress&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining. Here&amp;rsquo;s why:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Technopoly</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-08-16-book-review-technopoly-v2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 23:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-08-16-book-review-technopoly-v2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- Introduction --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Technopoly: The Surrender of Culture to Technology&lt;/em&gt;, Neil Postman argues that our infatuation with technology has insidiously eroded our culture. We gain much through technology, but it comes at a price; all too often we are blind to that price. This book seeks to call attention to the costs of a technology-focused society. I felt this poignantly because I, as a technology worker, know what that infatuation feels like.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Amusing Ourselves to Death</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-06-07-amusing-ourselves-to-death/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-06-07-amusing-ourselves-to-death/</guid>
      <description>Overview # The primary thrust of this book is that television has degraded our mode of public discourse. Our news, politics, education, and even religion are delivered to us primarily through television, where they were once delivered via the written word. This transformation of medium is not irrelevant: just as poetry doesn&amp;rsquo;t survive fully intact when translated from one language to another, likewise ideas do not survive translation of medium.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masks</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-05-23-masks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2020-05-23-masks/</guid>
      <description>Masks have become a hot issue. Here&amp;rsquo;s my 2¢.
Summary # I think everyone should wear a mask, unless they have a compelling medical reason not to.
Look at it this way: a mask will either help you and those around you, or it will do no harm—beyond a little social awkwardness. If we look at the trade-offs in a game-theory-style matrix, we get:
| | Masks Help | Masks don&amp;rsquo;t help | |&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;-+&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;+&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;| | Wear a mask | +100 | 0 | | Don&amp;rsquo;t wear a mask | -100 | 0 |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Internships!</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-16-internships/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 02:42:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-16-internships/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re a student at BYU, (or maybe even if you aren&amp;rsquo;t) BYU has a fantastic study-abroad program. I believe there are over 100 different programs. I might do an internship in Berlin some time but we&amp;rsquo;ll see if that pans out. :) Check out the list at kennedy.byu.edu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DuckDuckGo</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-15-duckduckgo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 05:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-15-duckduckgo/</guid>
      <description>DuckDuckGo is a search engine. Like Google Search, you just throw some keywords into a box and get a list of results. Lots of people use Google, but I don&amp;rsquo;t. DuckDuckGo works better for me, and this is why.
The Duck ## Consistent Results Did you know that Google will give you different search results, based on who you are and what you have searched for in the past? This is called a filter bubble, and it&amp;rsquo;s annoying and dangerous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comments</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-06-comments/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 02:55:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-06-comments/</guid>
      <description>I got Disqus working! You&amp;rsquo;ll notice at the bottom of the page is now a place to leave comments.
Disqus has their privacy policy here. They make money through advertising, which is unfortunate, because that means they&amp;rsquo;re selling some of your (and my) data to third parties. That&amp;rsquo;s pretty common these days. :-/
If you don&amp;rsquo;t want to be tracked, you can enable content blockers in Safari by going to Preferences (⌘-,) &amp;gt; Websites &amp;gt; Content Blockers and toggling the blocker:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Organization Theory</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-05-organization-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 01:19:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2019-01-05-organization-theory/</guid>
      <description>Life is messy. We devote a lot of time and effort into managing that chaos. I thought of a little &amp;ldquo;theory&amp;rdquo;, if you will, that helps me.
The Home Theory # Everything needs a home. The class of things that need homes is broad. It includes:
School assignments Legal documents Pictures Recipies Ideas Projects Books Charging cables Tools etc. The home needs to suit the thing that goes there. I have found that getting this right is really tricky.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Best Two Years</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-11-20-the-best-two-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 06:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-11-20-the-best-two-years/</guid>
      <description>September 30th marked two years since I arrived home from serving a two-year mission for the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. The mission is colloquially referred to as &amp;ldquo;the best two years&amp;rdquo;. (There is a movie about missionaries, which I have not seen, by this title.)
My time on the mission did constitute the best two years of my life. I grew and learned so much in that time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leaving Facebook</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-06-23-leaving-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 19:29:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-06-23-leaving-facebook/</guid>
      <description>Deutsche Übersetzung folgt.
I&amp;rsquo;ve left* Facebook.
There&amp;rsquo;s an asterisk there. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to delete my account, but I&amp;rsquo;m no longer checking Facebook more than once or twice a month, if that. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to be a recluse—below are a few ways to contact me that I do check far more often than Facebook. I want to be your friend, but I&amp;rsquo;d rather that friendship be through a real connection rather than some online &amp;ldquo;status&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Wedding</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-05-26-marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 18:12:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-05-26-marriage/</guid>
      <description>I got married last week!
I met Sarah almost five years ago on trek.1 We stayed in touch afterwards, and look where we ended up! Below are some stories from our courtship.
First time seeing each other # It was the first day of trek. I found my family and sat down at the most extreme end of the bench. I got to know my trek brothers a little bit, but mostly kept to myself.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Light</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-02-19-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 22:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-02-19-light/</guid>
      <description>I came across a quote posted by a friend of mine that read:
The difference between spiritualism and religion is that spiritualism is pro-light, while religion is anti-sin.
Or something to that effect. This quote bothered me because I felt that it maligned religion. I asked this friend for some clarification; it seemed clear from their response that they had had a rather negative experience with religion. They explained that they felt that religion (in general) micro-manages the lives of its adherents and focuses on telling people what they can&amp;rsquo;t do.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
