<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>career on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in career on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Metric Worship, or: How a bad manager wrecked a (small) company</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-02-21_metric_worship/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-02-21_metric_worship/</guid>
      <description>I once worked as a part of a company with four employees, all of us programmers. We formed a sort of daughter company with a bigger—though still modest-sized—company that handled our payroll and whatnot. Our work directly helped the parent company, but we were organizationally independent development-wise. I really liked working with that small team: we had a one-hour meeting each week to plan out our work, and a short, casual stand-up each morning to get things rolling.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changes in Career Aspirations</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2023-02-03_aspiration_changes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2023-02-03_aspiration_changes/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;#39;s interesting for me to reflect on how my aspirations have changed as I&amp;#39;ve grown up. When I was a little kid I wanted to be a computer programmer like my daddy. I wanted to have my own cubicle and a work station and write Perl programs all day long in Emacs.
There was a phase where I had to shake my head at that—a cubicle-dweller? Seriously? After experiencing some open-office work spaces, the shoulder-high walls afforded a privacy and sound muffling that any hipster coder would be envious of.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
