<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Delight on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/delight/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Delight on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/delight/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started With Lock Picking</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2025-08-21_lockpicking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2025-08-21_lockpicking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are few sounds as satisfying to me as a lock popping open, especially when it&amp;rsquo;s a well-machined lock that makes a nice, crisp &amp;ldquo;chink!&amp;rdquo; sound as the shackle releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is some suggestions I gave to a friend of mine who wanted to get started in lock picking. Please consult your local laws to know the ins and outs around the hobby. Nothing here is legal advice. Also, while I do link to a few product pages, I never have and never will take commissions for material on this blog. I am recommending these tools because &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; like them, and not for any financial gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rules for Lock Picking&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two big rules to follow when picking locks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Only pick locks that you own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never pick locks that are in use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rule 1 should be fairly obvious: picking other locks can be a criminal offense. Rule 2 is for your sake: picking a lock can, on rare occasions, break the lock. If the lock is in use, you might have to get bolt cutters or a big drill to fix the problem destructively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;picks-and-tensioning&#34;&gt;
  Picks &amp;amp; Tensioning
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#picks-and-tensioning&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tools matter. The biggest piece of advice is this: &lt;strong&gt;never buy picks off Amazon!&lt;/strong&gt; Those pick sets are made with cheap steel that gets caught in keyways and provides lousy feedback. I thought I was a bad picker for many years—and that is true—but it was also due in large part to how my tools were holding me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember: a few high-quality tools is better than a big set of nearly useless ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get picks from &lt;a href=&#34;https://jimylongs.com/&#34;&gt;JimyLongs&lt;/a&gt;. They are the best. They will last you forever. Everyone on &lt;a href=&#34;https://reddit.com/r/lockpicking&#34;&gt;r/lockpicking&lt;/a&gt; loves them. They are remarkably affordable. They&amp;rsquo;re versatile and comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would start with the Basics and Intermediate sets. They&amp;rsquo;re both 0.019&amp;quot; thick, which is a touch thinner than the picks you were working with (0.025&amp;quot;) which means feedback is a little more subtle, but it&amp;rsquo;s easier to get into more keyways. The two sets will also get you a nice selection of turning tools. The z-bar TOK (Top Of Keyway) turners are really nice to use; I almost exclusively use TOK turners now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the Covert Instruments ergo turners. They make practicing so comfortable.&lt;label class=&#34;margin-toggle sidenote-number&#34; for=&#34;sn1&#34;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input id=&#34;sn1&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;sidenote&#34;&gt;
Left-handed pickers: the ergo turners will probably not work for you—sorry!
&lt;/span&gt;
They might go on sale around Black Friday, so watch out for that. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t bother much with other stuff from CI unless you see something that you really like. I do have the Covert Companion with some extension kits for EDC-style (Every Day Cary) portability, but it&amp;rsquo;s rather terrible for practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://jimylongs.com/products&#34;&gt;https://jimylongs.com/products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://covertinstruments.com/products/ergo-turner-set&#34;&gt;https://covertinstruments.com/products/ergo-turner-set&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-locks&#34;&gt;
  Practice Locks
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#practice-locks&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great resource is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://lpubelts.com/#/locks&#34;&gt;LPU Belt Explorer&lt;/a&gt;. This is a big categorization of pretty much any lock you&amp;rsquo;ll ever run into broken down by complexity. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lpubelts.com/#/locks?tab=search&amp;amp;search=2455f0ae&amp;amp;id=2455f0ae&amp;amp;name=Master_Lock_140_141&#34;&gt;here is the entry for the Master Lock 140&lt;/a&gt;—a great beginner lock. The locks are organized according to &amp;ldquo;belts&amp;rdquo; like those in Karate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find Brinks laminated and brass padlocks at Walmart. These are both in the yellow belt tier and are fine locks for getting started. Once you start wanting better locks, I have found that locks from Abus tend to be well-machined and give good feedback. Sometimes a crappy Master Lock can be hard to open because it&amp;rsquo;s greasy or something on the inside and that can totally kill feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A dirty old lock is typically harder to open than a clean, well-machined higher-tier lock.&lt;/strong&gt; Not having feedback when picking a lock is like trying to assemble a puzzle while blindfolded. If you get a used lock, you might want to clean it first to get that feedback back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you go higher, the Abus 55/40 is a fantastic orange belt. The American 1100 is a popular green belt. I just bought 7 of these things off of Ebay. The Master Lock LOTO lock (plastic body; lots of colors) is another excellent green belt that will force you to get a feel for spool pins. That&amp;rsquo;s as high as I&amp;rsquo;ve gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around Black Friday definitely check out the Covert Instruments practice lock: it&amp;rsquo;s re-pinable and comes with a bunch of pins so you can practice getting a feel for different bitting and security pins. My brother got me this set with the set of picks I let you borrow for Christmas, and the lock has been super helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;community&#34;&gt;
  Community
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#community&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like Reddit, r/lockpicking is a great place to hang out, ask questions, and get tips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of good YouTubers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lockpicking Lawyer (of course): He focuses more on picking commercial locks and pointing out their security flaws. Not necessarily the best resource for learning lock picking. (His &amp;ldquo;inside perspective&amp;rdquo; series is great though!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lockpicking Dev: This channels has a little bit more about how to actually pick locks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lady Locks: She had a video that helped me get my first American 1100 open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fish Picks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sandman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tl-dr&#34;&gt;
  TL;DR
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#tl-dr&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start with these picks and locks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basics set from JimyLongs lock picks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master Lock 140, Brinks laminated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Level up with these:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Intermediate set from JimyLongs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Covert Instruments ergo-turners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locks from Abus, ACE hardware (their brass padlock is &lt;em&gt;insane&lt;/em&gt;&amp;mdash;I have not yet opened it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decide where to go from there!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How, Where, and Why I Take Notes</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-07-29_note_mediums/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-07-29_note_mediums/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I take a blend of digital and hand-written notes. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a hodgepodge, but it&amp;rsquo;s working. I used to lean heavily into full-digital notes, but I started drifting towards a mixture of digital and hand-written notes. Initially it was complicated, but I think I&amp;rsquo;m converging on a good setup. What I describe here will continue to evolve I am sure, but I am enjoying where it&amp;rsquo;s currently at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pen-and-paper-is-best-for-thinking&#34;&gt;
  Pen and paper is best for thinking
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#pen-and-paper-is-best-for-thinking&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen down the fountain pen rabbit hole. I used to write with a Pilot G2 pen, and I loved how dark ink was. The primary drawback was that it bled through the paper of my Leuchtturm notebooks a little bit. I also had some problems with the extra-fine 0.38 pens: after a few months of use, they&amp;rsquo;d break before all the gel ink had been expended. This was frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I write with a Lamy Al-Star with an extra-fine nib. I use Pilot&amp;rsquo;s black &lt;em&gt;take-sumi iroshizuku&lt;/em&gt; ink. It is &lt;em&gt;lovely&lt;/em&gt; to write with this pen. Compared to the G2, the fountain pen writes just as fine as the 0.38 G2, but the ink doesn&amp;rsquo;t skip, the tip never breaks, and the ink doesn&amp;rsquo;t bleed through the paper at all. Sure, the fountain pen requires a little more maintenance than a gel or ballpoint pen, but it is fun to have a little mechanical thing to maintain and form simple rituals around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting the fountain pen had the curious effect of making me want to take &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; notes by hand. I started writing a lot more. But I have a bunch of infrastructure set up for digital note taking, so when I initially started writing more, I would get a little lost as to where I had put certain notes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did find that I enjoyed writing my thoughts out—it was like doing a one-person rubber-duck session. I strongly believe that writing helps you think: it forces you to be explicit with your thoughts and it helps you notice gaps in your thinking. This can push you to answer questions that you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have asked otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;quasi-digital-for-classes&#34;&gt;
  Quasi-digital for classes
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#quasi-digital-for-classes&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In class I take notes on an iPad with an Apple Pencil. I like that I can keep all my notes for all my classes with me at all times. I also like that I can write in different colors when needed, the ability to download or take a picture of a slide and mark it up, or do some lightweight diagraming. I feel like it gives me the best of both worlds: I get the storage, versatility, and searchability of digital notes, but I get the memory benefits of handwritten notes since I am &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;typing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;full-digital-for-research&#34;&gt;
  Full digital for research
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#full-digital-for-research&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Backlinks:&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The set of notes that link &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; a given note. Suppose note A has a link to note B. If I am looking at note B, then A will be in the set of B&amp;rsquo;s backlinks.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I have something that I am researching, I typically keep notes in a plain-text file on my computer. (I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; most of the time, naturally.) This lets me link and search through my notes really easily. Being on a computer means that it is easy to copy-paste things I want to remember and then store links to recover the source. I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://protesilaos.com/emacs/denote&#34;&gt;Denote&lt;/a&gt; to organize my notes; Denote lets me format my notes consistently, as well as recover backlinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun aside: I recently &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/protesilaos/denote/commit/4318efe7e8ce2bcd2cafa386a903054273203fd5&#34;&gt;contributed some code to Denote&lt;/a&gt; that adds an indicator in the mode-line if the currently-visited note has a backlink. I like getting a heads-up that there&amp;rsquo;s some digging to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also will put notes that I made by hand during a thinking session into my Denote files after they&amp;rsquo;ve had a little time to marinate in my head. I will typically use this step to flesh out ideas that I only got in skeleton form in my notebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like Denote: it is simple, requires no external dependencies, and it plays nicely with synching systems. Today, thanks to my tag system, links, backlinks, and some searching, I ran into some notes I had taken a year ago and forgot about—but now these notes are helping me with my work right now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-what-i-write-and-where&#34;&gt;
  Summary: what I write and where
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#summary-what-i-write-and-where&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After thinking a little bit about what mode of note taking benefits most from a given medium, I came up with the following system for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Meeting with my advisor&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I take meeting notes by hand on paper, usually in my notebook.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Thinking through something&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Again, hand-written, usually on my Rhodia pads as these are typically ephemeral notes. If I get a good idea, I&amp;rsquo;ll write it down in my notebook and then transfer it to my digital Denote notes later.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Reading notes&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;If I am reading a technical paper or book that I want to understand, I&amp;rsquo;ll take these notes in my notebook.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Research lab notes&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Digital. I have a template that I fill out every day that helps me keep track of basic information and links all of my daily lab notes to a big note for the whole project. This makes it easy for me to go to that project note and flip through the backlinks.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Class notes&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;While I only have one more class left, I still take class notes on my iPad. I feel like class notes benefit the most from a digital-handwriting hybrid.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you adopt the setup I have? No. You should arrive to your own system yourself. The only thing I would advise anyone to take from my experience is that you should put a little time and effort into being &lt;em&gt;intentional&lt;/em&gt; about how you take notes and how your organize them. You need to find a system that works for &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, and only &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; can do the work to make that happen.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Font</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-08-01_a_new_font/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-08-01_a_new_font/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week I created a custom build of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/be5invis/Iosevka&#34;&gt;Iosevka&lt;/a&gt; font. I&amp;rsquo;ve used &lt;a href=&#34;https://input.djr.com/&#34;&gt;Input Mono&lt;/a&gt; for a long time now, and was very happy with it. However, it was missing a few glyphs that I wanted to use. Moreover, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a license for the Input font to use on e.g. my blog. Iosevka is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/be5invis/Iosevka/blob/master/doc/custom-build.md&#34;&gt;stupendously customizable&lt;/a&gt;, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d see if I could get something close to Input&amp;rsquo;s styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iosevka&amp;rsquo;s default style is &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; narrow. However, I discovered that the width of Iosevka &lt;em&gt;extended&lt;/em&gt; at 13pt matched Input at 12pt exactly. Here&amp;rsquo;s a side-by-side comparison: the first picture is with Input Mono, and the second is with my new &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/ashton314/iosevka-output&#34;&gt;Iosevka Output&lt;/a&gt; font:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/img/input_view.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;Figure 1: Input Mono at 12pt font&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;figure-number&#34;&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;Input Mono at 12pt font&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/img/iosevka_view.png&#34;
    alt=&#34;Figure 2: Iosevka Output at 13pt font&#34;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;figure-number&#34;&gt;Figure 2: &lt;/span&gt;Iosevka Output at 13pt font&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loose a few lines with the Iosevka font, but that&amp;rsquo;s a deliberate choice as its ascenders are pretty tall. I originally had &lt;code&gt;leading = 1100&lt;/code&gt; in the build plan, which matched Input exactly, but I decided that this was more legible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t that hard either. Turns out, there&amp;rsquo;s a predefined stylistic set (&lt;code&gt;ss18&lt;/code&gt;) that matches almost all the Input characters well. Some features that I made sure were present:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Double-storey &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt;: I find this more legible as I don&amp;rsquo;t mistake these characters for &lt;code&gt;o&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;y&lt;/code&gt; respectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tailed-and-serif &lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt;: the curved bottom differentiates it clearly from &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;I&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Term&amp;rdquo;-style spacing: I didn&amp;rsquo;t like characters such as &lt;code&gt;→&lt;/code&gt; taking up more than a single character&amp;rsquo;s width. Looks pretty, but messes up some of my UI elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few more tweaks that I&amp;rsquo;ve made to the font, and I&amp;rsquo;m likely to tweak it some more. I&amp;rsquo;m still getting used to this Iosevka style, but I&amp;rsquo;m going to drive it for a week or so to give it a fair shake. It&amp;rsquo;s growing on me for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to try it out, head over to &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/ashton314/iosevka-output/&#34;&gt;my Codeberg repo&lt;/a&gt; and download the build artifact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;building-iosevka&#34;&gt;
  Building Iosevka
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#building-iosevka&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll need &lt;code&gt;nodejs&lt;/code&gt; (ugh) and &lt;code&gt;ttfautohint&lt;/code&gt; installed. See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/be5invis/Iosevka/blob/master/doc/custom-build.md&#34;&gt;docs for custom Iosevka builds&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you clone the Iosevka repository, be sure to not clone all 20 Gb of history:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#d8dee9;background-color:#2e3440;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;git clone --depth &lt;span style=&#34;color:#b48ead&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; https://github.com/be5invis/Iosevka
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve got the build repo cloned, copy my &lt;code&gt;private-build-plans.toml&lt;/code&gt; file into the root of the Iosevka directory, and run according to the directions in the Iosevka project.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ode to Used Book Stores</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-08-03_used_books/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-08-03_used_books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I get a little money I buy books; and if any is left I buy food and clothes.&lt;br&gt;
— Erasmus of Rotterdam&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used bookstores are my arch nemesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two such stores in disturbingly close proximity to me. The first is Boomerang Books—within a short walk of my house and right next to Burgers Supreme (almost as dangerous)—and they carry textbooks at a fifth of the original price. Last time I went there I walked out with a book on graph theory I most certainly don&amp;rsquo;t need. The second is Pioneer Book. My wife and I went there on a date a couple of months ago. I walked out with a dozen books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wallet has suffered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What keeps me hooked is that my wallet has suffered &lt;em&gt;much less&lt;/em&gt; than it would if they were not used books, though!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The serendipity is what gets me. I was walking up the stairs when I passed a copy of &lt;em&gt;Walden&lt;/em&gt; be Emerson that was waiting to be sorted and shelved. I picked it up and added it to the pile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how much more my bookshelf can take. The books are already stacked two deep. I just need to make time, dig in, and start reading. Maybe I can give back some of those wonderful books after I&amp;rsquo;ve finished them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marked Man</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2019-01-24-marked-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 03:54:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2019-01-24-marked-man/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Marked Man (mm) is a little program I wrote to view Markdown files like UNIX man pages. (Because who wants to leave their terminal just to open a file?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It uses &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; to convert between Markdown and the &lt;code&gt;groff&lt;/code&gt; format. As a happy side-effect, this program can read basically &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; as a man page: HTML, LaTeX, Word files (seriously), ePub, etc. Anything that Pandoc can read, Marked Man can handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing&#34;&gt;
  Installing
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#installing&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m working on getting this set up with &lt;a href=&#34;brew.sh&#34;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt;. For now, check out my GitHub repository &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ashton314/homebrew-mm&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
