<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AI stands for “Artificial Inanity”</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2025-08-04_artifical_inanity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2025-08-04_artifical_inanity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s something icky about LLM-generated text when you think it&amp;rsquo;s written by a human. I think I finally put my finger on one reason why I feel this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note on the title: &amp;ldquo;Artificial Inanity&amp;rdquo; comes from Neal Stephenson&amp;rsquo;s novel &lt;em&gt;Anathem&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work I was sent a long design document and asked for my thoughts on it. As I read, I had a really hard time following it. Eventually I guessed correctly (confirmed via a follow-up conversation I had with the &amp;ldquo;author&amp;rdquo;&lt;label class=&#34;margin-toggle sidenote-number&#34; for=&#34;sn1&#34;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input id=&#34;sn1&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;sidenote&#34;&gt;
I have &amp;ldquo;author&amp;rdquo; in quotes because, if a machine wrote it, you don&amp;rsquo;t merit being called the &lt;em&gt;author&lt;/em&gt; of the work.
&lt;/span&gt;
) that an LLM had generated the majority of the document. Parts of it &lt;em&gt;sounded&lt;/em&gt; like a decent design document, but there was just way too much fluff that served only to confuse me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I read technical documents, I read to understand the content. In this mode of reading, I operate under the assumption that the author had a reason for choosing the words they did, and that every sentence is there to convey something that the author wishes me to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This mode fails when an LLM or the like has generated the text. When I read something I know came out of a computer&amp;rsquo;s probabilistic sampling of a token-space, I have read knowing that every statement might be some hallucinated slop or incidental filler. I &lt;em&gt;cannot&lt;/em&gt; trust that the human operator&amp;rsquo;s intent is expressed by the machine. In fact, I am confident that it is often &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;, but I have to waste tremendous effort trying to find that gap. Reading slop text when I think I&amp;rsquo;m reading real text is exhausting: since I am not on the alert for hallucinations or irrelevancies, every turn of phrase that seems out of place causes me to wonder &lt;em&gt;why that phrase it there&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;what am I missing&lt;/em&gt; when in reality, such questions are ill formed: that was just a phrase composed by accident that &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; good but actually is devoid of much intent at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intent&lt;/em&gt; is the core thing: the &lt;em&gt;lack&lt;/em&gt; of intent is what makes reading AI-slop so revolting. There needs to be a human intent—human will and human care—behind everything that is demanded of our care and attention. Even if you agree with Rolland Barthes&amp;rsquo;&lt;label class=&#34;margin-toggle sidenote-number&#34; for=&#34;sn2&#34;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input id=&#34;sn2&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;sidenote&#34;&gt;
The author of &lt;em&gt;The Death of the Author&lt;/em&gt;, and essay where Barthes argues that focusing on the author&amp;rsquo;s intent is fruitless—the meaning of a text is the effect it has on the audience.
&lt;/span&gt;
views on literary criticism, the fact that there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an author who put care and intent into a work imbues that work with infinitely more meaning than if it were spat out by a machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterfeits to human connection will—unfortunately—always be in demand. The multi-billion dollar industry churning out pornography is proof enough. People will probably always, from here on out, be using LLMs to cheat their way through classes and themselves out of learning. Some might turn to them for some faux-companionship. Others will be prompting themselves to death by offloading more and more of their reasoning to machines, convinced that the computer—like a slot machine—somehow will let them win bigger in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; saying that LLMs are worthless—they are marvels of engineering and can solve some particularly thorny problems that have confounded us for decades. But it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that, no matter how capable these machines get, they are not humans. And no human is so worthless as to be replaceable with a machine.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citations with Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2019-02-06-citations-with-pandoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 05:03:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2019-02-06-citations-with-pandoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I figured out how to get &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org&#34;&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; to automatically generate MLA citations for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used Pandoc and the Biblatex bibliography format. What&amp;rsquo;s nice about this is that you can enter in all the information you know about the source, keep it nice and organized in a file, and then change the citation style on the fly. Imagine if you thought you had to use MLA, but then realized you needed to switch to APA citation styles. You can do that instantly with Pandoc and Biblatex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you&amp;rsquo;ll need &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackage.haskell.org/package/pandoc-citeproc&#34;&gt;pandoc-citeproc&lt;/a&gt;. (Instructions to install are on the Pandoc website. If you&amp;rsquo;re running macOS, you can use &lt;a href=&#34;brew.sh&#34;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; to install with &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;brew install pandoc-citeproc&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, create a bibliography file. Pandoc can work with many different formats, outlined &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org/MANUAL.html#citations&#34;&gt;in their documentation&lt;/a&gt;, but I&amp;rsquo;ll show an example with Biblatex, the bibliography database format used with LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example markdown file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;---
title: Irresponsible Encryption
author: Ashton Wiersdorf
date: \today
bibliography: research/refs.bib
link-citations: true
cls: Modern Language Association 8th edition
---

Imagine a world where every phone call was tapped, where every purchase online could compromise your credit card, and where every one of your online accounts could be hacked. Imagine if every email you sent were scanned, analyzed, and the findings sold to the highest bidder. Imagine if your health, financial, and shopping records were public. That would be the end of our modern life as we know it. That is a real possiblity we are facing. (Especially if you use Gmail—Google has scanned the contents of emails in the past to serve targeted ads. [See @scroogled_blog]) Governments across the world—from the United States to Australia—are pushing or have passed legislation that mandates &amp;quot;exceptional access mechanisms&amp;quot;—means by which they can break encryption if they have a warrant to do so. They point to cases where criminals—from drug dealers to terrorists—have used encryption to conceal evidence against themselves. However, what they are asking for would have its consequences.



\pagebreak

# References
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note how I have &lt;code&gt;bibliography: research/refs.bib&lt;/code&gt; at the top of the file. That lets Pandoc know where to go to find the biblography file. Then you can have a database file like this stored in &lt;code&gt;research/refs.bib&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;@online{scroogled_blog,
	Annotation = {Ars Technica reports on this---the scary part is that Google was scanning emails in the first place.},
	Author = {Diane Greene},
	Crossref = {ars_scroogled},
	Date = {2017-06-23},
	Title = {As G Suite gains traction in the enterprise, G Suite&#39;s Gmail and consumer Gmail to more closely align},
	Url = {https://blog.google/products/gmail/g-suite-gains-traction-in-the-enterprise-g-suites-gmail-and-consumer-gmail-to-more-closely-align/},
	Urldate = {2019-02-05},
	Bdsk-Url-1 = {https://blog.google/products/gmail/g-suite-gains-traction-in-the-enterprise-g-suites-gmail-and-consumer-gmail-to-more-closely-align/}}

@online{ars_scroogled,
	Author = {Ron Amadeo},
	Date = {2017-06-23},
	Title = {Scroogled no more: Gmail won&#39;t scan e-mails for ads personalization},
	Url = {https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2017/06/gmail-will-no-longer-scan-e-mails-for-ad-personalization/},
	Urldate = {2019-02-05},
	Bdsk-Url-1 = {https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2017/06/gmail-will-no-longer-scan-e-mails-for-ad-personalization/}}

...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each entry has a &lt;em&gt;cite key&lt;/em&gt;: something that lets you refer to the citation from within your document. Note how in the markdown file I wrote &lt;code&gt;[See @scroogled_blog]&lt;/code&gt;. That gets replaced with the following in the final product:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…Google has scanned the contents of emails in the past to serve targeted ads. (See Greene 2017)…&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And at the end of the paper, I get a nice-looking citation like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greene, Diane. 2017. “As G Suite Gains Traction in the Enterprise, G Suite’s Gmail and Consumer Gmail to More Closely Align.” June 23, 2017. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blog.google/products/gmail/g-suite-gains-traction-in-the-enterprise-g-suites-gmail-and-consumer-gmail-to-more-closely-align/&#34;&gt;https://blog.google/products/gmail/g-suite-gains-traction-in-the-enterprise-g-suites-gmail-and-consumer-gmail-to-more-closely-align/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To generate the finished product, I simply run &lt;code&gt;pandoc --filter pandoc-citeproc paper.md -o paper.pdf&lt;/code&gt;. Poof! Nicely formatted and automatic citations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To change the citation style, simply alter what is on the line starting with &lt;code&gt;cls:&lt;/code&gt; in the header. You can find a list of valid styles &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zotero.org/styles&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, with more information &lt;a href=&#34;https://citationstyles.org/authors/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Good luck with your papers!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
