<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>books on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/books/</link>
    <description>Recent content in books on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Ode to Used Book Stores</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-08-03_used_books/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-08-03_used_books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I get a little money I buy books; and if any is left I buy food and clothes.&lt;br&gt;
— Erasmus of Rotterdam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Used bookstores are my arch nemesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two such stores in disturbingly close proximity to me. The first is Boomerang Books—within a short walk of my house and right next to Burgers Supreme (almost as dangerous)—and they carry textbooks at a fifth of the original price. Last time I went there I walked out with a book on graph theory I most certainly don&amp;rsquo;t need. The second is Pioneer Book. My wife and I went there on a date a couple of months ago. I walked out with a dozen books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wallet has suffered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What keeps me hooked is that my wallet has suffered &lt;em&gt;much less&lt;/em&gt; than it would if they were not used books, though!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The serendipity is what gets me. I was walking up the stairs when I passed a copy of &lt;em&gt;Walden&lt;/em&gt; be Emerson that was waiting to be sorted and shelved. I picked it up and added it to the pile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how much more my bookshelf can take. The books are already stacked two deep. I just need to make time, dig in, and start reading. Maybe I can give back some of those wonderful books after I&amp;rsquo;ve finished them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
