<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Family on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/family/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Family on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/family/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>TV Shows for Kids</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2025-04-20_kids_shows/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2025-04-20_kids_shows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was in my early 20s, I vowed that I would keep my kids from watching any amount of television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, sometimes you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need a break as a parent. A good show can keep your kid entertained while you perform necessary tasks like preparing a meal, doing the dishes, or getting just enough extra sleep to not blow your top or doze off in the car while you drive your kid to preschool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I have had a change of heart: TV can be a tool, but not all TV programs are created equal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, here is my tier list of the shows I&amp;rsquo;ve seen or heard about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;s-tier&#34;&gt;
  S-tier
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#s-tier&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the shows that I am fine with my kid watching any time. They are well-written, low-stimulus, and never get annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do I care so much about low-stimulus shows? I don&amp;rsquo;t want my kids getting hooked on dopamine rushes. I&amp;rsquo;d rather that they play imaginatively as much as possible. Low-stimulus shows help by not desensitizing kids to the gentler kind of happiness that comes through creative play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bluey&#34;&gt;
  Bluey
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#bluey&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How could it not be &lt;em&gt;Bluey&lt;/em&gt;?! It&amp;rsquo;s a low-stimulus show about parenting that kids happen to enjoy as well. The dad, Bandit, is an enthusiastic, clever, engaged parent who sometimes messes up but always makes up for it. The mum, Chili, is loving, firm, hard-working, and creative. The relationships are positive and realistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite episodes are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Camping&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This one makes me tear up. I initially saw Jean-Luc&amp;rsquo;s departure as a metaphor for death and Chili&amp;rsquo;s words as a hope to see our friends again in the hereafter. But then my wife pointed out that the episode is essentially the Star Trek episode &lt;em&gt;Darmok&lt;/em&gt; where the captain of the Enterprise (Jean-Luc Picard—the name should have been a clue) must learn how to communicate with someone who speaks a strange language.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;The Sign&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The hour-long 3rd-season finale is an absolute onslaught of emotional sucker-punches if you&amp;rsquo;ve watched the entire show.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Granny Mobile&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Nothing particularly deep in this episode, but it is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; funny.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are more. &lt;em&gt;Bluey&lt;/em&gt; deserves all the hype it gets. It&amp;rsquo;s that good. If you have a toddler, watch &lt;em&gt;Bluey&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;puffin-rock&#34;&gt;
  Puffin Rock
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#puffin-rock&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feels like an Irish-flavored &lt;em&gt;Bluey&lt;/em&gt;-type show, but with Irish-accented puffins. Sweet show with a pretty animation style. Most episodes are just about the main character, Oona, exploring the island. Less anthropomorphic than &lt;em&gt;Bluey&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-tier&#34;&gt;
  A-tier
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#a-tier&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good shows that don&amp;rsquo;t quite rise to the level of &lt;em&gt;Bluey&lt;/em&gt; and aren&amp;rsquo;t as visually beautiful as &lt;em&gt;Puffin Rock&lt;/em&gt; but are still fun and occasionally educational.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;little-einsteins&#34;&gt;
  Little Einsteins
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#little-einsteins&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four kids fly around in a &amp;ldquo;Rocket&amp;rdquo;. Each episode features a work of classical music and some art by a famous artist. The kids never fight—the whole show is about them solving problems. The best part is that my kid can now recognize lots of different important classical pieces and enjoys listening to them. Occasionally the episodes get a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; annoying because of how formulaic they are, but maybe that&amp;rsquo;s good for the kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;blue-s-clues&#34;&gt;
  Blue&amp;rsquo;s Clues
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#blue-s-clues&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up watching &lt;em&gt;Blue&amp;rsquo;s Clues&lt;/em&gt; and it&amp;rsquo;s still such a nice, sweet show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;b-tier&#34;&gt;
  B-tier
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#b-tier&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are shows that we will turn on if we have to. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t consider them &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;, but they are moderately annoying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;if-you-give-a-mouse-a-cookie&#34;&gt;
  If You Give A Mouse A Cookie
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#if-you-give-a-mouse-a-cookie&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a TV show based off of the series of children&amp;rsquo;s books by Laura Numeroff and Felicia Bond. The show is… fine. Most of the characters seem to have a sense of helplessness when something gets lost/broken and they feel that the circumstances &amp;ldquo;…will be ruined—forever!&amp;quot;&lt;label class=&#34;margin-toggle sidenote-number&#34; for=&#34;sn1&#34;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;
&lt;input id=&#34;sn1&#34; class=&#34;margin-toggle&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;sidenote&#34;&gt;
This is a phrase that I am &lt;em&gt;pretty&lt;/em&gt; sure crops up in every episode. Ugh.
&lt;/span&gt;
At least half the episodes involve some &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacGuffin&#34;&gt;MacGuffin&lt;/a&gt; rolling down a hill to a pond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, it&amp;rsquo;s not a &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; show, but sometimes my daughter will start talking like Mouse with one-word requests for things like &amp;ldquo;thirsty&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;hungry&amp;rdquo; instead of speaking in full sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;c-tier&#34;&gt;
  C-tier
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#c-tier&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are shows that I don&amp;rsquo;t consider actively harmful, but I strongly dislike because of how annoying they are or because my kid picks up bad behaviors from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;daniel-tiger&#34;&gt;
  Daniel Tiger
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#daniel-tiger&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface, this is the perfect show: it&amp;rsquo;s a spin-off of &lt;em&gt;Mr. Roger&amp;rsquo;s Neighborhood&lt;/em&gt;, the animation gentle and low-stimulus, and it&amp;rsquo;s moderately cute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But oh—oh how deceptive it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Tiger displays an impressive degree of learned helplessness and timidity. All of the &amp;ldquo;problems&amp;rdquo; that he encounters in the show are invented and stupid. E.g., it is raining outside so we can&amp;rsquo;t play on the beach—grrr I&amp;rsquo;m mad and now I need help calming down from a total meltdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; thing from this rainy-beach episode is when the kids drag in &lt;em&gt;several wheelbarrows&amp;rsquo; worth of sand onto the living room carpet&lt;/em&gt; and, when the mom comes in and gets angry, Daniel tells the mom to take a deep breath and calm down from her slightly agitated state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If my kid ever dragged several cubic meters of sand into any part of my house, I reserve the right to be upset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, cute on the surface, aggravating underneath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;f-tier&#34;&gt;
  F-tier
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#f-tier&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not watched these shows. I&amp;rsquo;m too scared to go near them with a stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;cocomelon&#34;&gt;
  CoComelon
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#cocomelon&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CoComelon&lt;/em&gt; is the epitome of high-stimulus children&amp;rsquo;s programming. In every shot the camera is panning, no shot lasts more than 3 seconds, and the show&amp;rsquo;s developers &lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20250403005628/https://www.nytimes.com/2022/05/05/arts/television/cocomelon-moonbug-entertainment.html?user_id=bde5ab3cc9b4378d62ec514312d1791c&amp;amp;campaign_id=61&amp;amp;emc=edit_ts_20220505&amp;amp;instance_id=60520&amp;amp;nl=the-great-read&amp;amp;regi_id=54686842&amp;amp;segment_id=91384&amp;amp;te=1&#34;&gt;utilize a tool they call &amp;ldquo;The Distraction&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; to determine when scenes are insufficiently attention-grabbing: when a test subject (a small child) looks away from the show to look at a screen showing adults doing banal household chores, the animators will amp up the show at that point to keep kids dialed in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would rather not have my child&amp;rsquo;s dopamine receptors burned out by stimulus-overload.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look, if you like &lt;em&gt;CoComelon&lt;/em&gt;, I won&amp;rsquo;t judge you. If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering if you should pull it up for your kids, I would stay &lt;em&gt;far away&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fewer-shows-the-better&#34;&gt;
  The fewer shows the better
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-fewer-shows-the-better&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kids need to be bored. The more bored they are, the more time they have to be creative and develop an internal world. I do think it&amp;rsquo;s fine to have some TV—I grew up loving &lt;em&gt;Arthur&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cyber Chase&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Reading Rainbow&lt;/em&gt;. It is really nice to have half an hour to shower, eat, and get some chores done so I can better take care of my child. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to find good shows though. I hope this helps any parents out there looking for ideas. :) Hang in there—raising kids is &lt;strong&gt;the very best&lt;/strong&gt; experience this world has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Grandpa</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2023-03-15_grandpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2023-03-15_grandpa/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;
My grandfather G William Wiersdorf passed away Monday morning. He was 82 and survived COVID, a decades-long existence with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multiple_sclerosis&#34;&gt;MS&lt;/a&gt;, and World War II. While his health wasn&amp;#39;t the best, none of us were expecting this. You can read his obituary &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.premierfuneral.com/obituaries/G-William-Bill-Wiersdorf/#!/Obituary&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
German obituary
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
UPDATE 2023-03-18: I&amp;#39;ve translated my grandpa&amp;#39;s obituary into German. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
G William &amp;#34;Bill&amp;#34; Wiersdorf verstarb friedlich am 13. März 2023 mit seiner liebevollen Frau Kathy an seiner Seite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bill wurde am 11. Dezember 1940 zu Anna Marrie Hedwig Bohnenstengel Wiersdorf und Wilhelm Franz Wiersdorf in Beyersdorf, Landsberg, Brandenburg, Preußen, Deutschland als Günther Willi Klaus Wiersdorf geboren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bills Vater wurde im letzten Tagen des zweiten Weltkriegs von Russische Soldaten gefangen genommen und starb in einem Zivelarbeitslager im Russland. Bill und seine Mutter waren dann Flüchtlinge nach dem Krieg und zog häufig währen die nächste paar Jahren in Deutschland zwischen gutherzige Familien um. Im Juni 1951, wanderten Bill und seine Mutter in die Vereinigten Staaten aus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bill lernte Englisch und als Teenager arbeitete für seinen Onkel Walter Stover in seinem Bettwaren- und Möbelfabrik in Salt Lake City. Bill lernte Möbel zu bauen und Lastwagen zu fahren. Bill diente eine Mission für die Kirche Jesu Christi der Heiligen der Letzten Tagen in Deutschland, und während seines Aufenthalts nahm er Kontakt mit vielen seinem verlorenen Verwandten wieder auf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bill schloss sein Studium an der Universität von Utah ab mit einem Grad in Spanisch. Bill unterrichtete Spanisch und trainierte Basketball an der Olympus Junior High, und später unterrichtete er Spanisch und Deutsch und trainierte die Fußballmannschaft der Olympus High School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bill erkrankte 1995 an Multipler Sklerose, und deswegen vorzeitig in Rente ging. Die Krankheit raubte ihm nach und nach seinem Gehfähigkeit und damit auch viele Aktivitäten, die er liebte. Er fand Befriedigung bei seiner Arbeit an seiner Utah Enzyklopädie Website (OnlineUtah.com) und verbrachte Tausende von Stunden Fotos und schriftliches Material dafür zu erstellen und kuratieren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bevor er von MS erkrankte war, wurde er von seine körperliche Stärke und Ausdauer bekannt. Mit wenig Hilfe, baute er ein Haus im Bergen und dort für Jahren veranstaltete Jugendgruppen und Familientreffen. Im Winter grub Bill eine Viertelmeile &amp;#34;Rodelbahn&amp;#34; in den Schnee, damit die Kinder im Schlitten herunterfahren konnten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Nach MS war er für seiner geistliche Ausdauer bekannt. Obwohl die Krankheit sein Leben schwer machte, erlaubte Bill seinem Gesundheitszustand seine Seele in Geduld zu läutern. Bill folgte Jesus Christus nach und liebte es, andere Menschen wie er konnte zu dienen. Er liebte es auch, Zeit mit seiner Familie zu verbringen und freute sich besonders an seine wöchentlichen Video-Chats mit seinen Cousins, die in Deutschland wohnen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Bill hinterlässt seine Frau Kathy Pearson Wiersdorf, seine Kinder Scott (Ana) Wiersdorf, Ryan (Liz) Wiersdorf, Jason (Erin) Wiersdorf, Rachel Wiersdorf, dreizehn Enkelkinder und eine Urenkelin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
