<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tutorials on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/categories/tutorials/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tutorials on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/categories/tutorials/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Writing Racket Macros: define-syntax and phases</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-05-19_racket_macros/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-05-19_racket_macros/</guid>
      <description>There are a bunch of different ways of writing a macro in Racket. There are also some tricky things around phases to keep in mind. This is to help me keep them all straight.
3+1 ways to make a macro # This form:
(define-syntax-rule (foo args ...) (use args ...)) is equivalent to:
(define-syntax foo (syntax-rules () ([foo args ...] (use args ...)))) Which, is in turn equivalent to:
(define-syntax foo (λ (stx) (syntax-case stx () [(gensymed-foo args .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Make an Emacs Buffer Open the Way You Want</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-12-27_repl_buffer_on_the_right/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-12-27_repl_buffer_on_the_right/</guid>
      <description>Are you tired of having a particular buffer pop open in the wrong direction? Do you wish, for example, that the Racket REPL buffer showed up on the right in a vertical split, rather than below in a horizontal one? Look no further. I give you, display-buffer-alist:
(add-to-list &amp;#39;display-buffer-alist &amp;#39;(&amp;#34;\\*Racket REPL &amp;lt;/&amp;gt;\\*&amp;#34; (display-buffer-in-direction) (direction . right))) That little snippet will make sure when you hit C-c C-k inside of a racket-mode buffer, a REPL will pop up on the right-side instead of on the bottom.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuations—what are they?</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-11-17_continutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-11-17_continutations/</guid>
      <description>I had a friend ask me what continuations are, and why they&amp;#39;re useful. There&amp;#39;s a ton of literature about continuations; this is just a simple example meant to showcase something small and hopefully grokkable.
You will need to understand a little bit of Racket, but if you know any Scheme, that should be good enough. If you just want a quick primer, check out Learn X in Y minutes for Racket.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adding a Clock to the Tab-Bar in Emacs 28</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-20_adding_a_clock_to_emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-20_adding_a_clock_to_emacs/</guid>
      <description>Today I figured out how to add a tab-bar to Emacs. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like having it in the mode-line: it gets duplicated for every window and my mode-line space is precious. In contrast, the right side of the tab-bar was always blank.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>microKanren Reading</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-04_kanren/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-07-04_kanren/</guid>
      <description>μKanren (&amp;ldquo;micro-Kanren&amp;rdquo;) is a tiny, embeddable logic programming language. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to understand and implement in almost any language. It&amp;rsquo;s a great case study of an embedded language: unlike other common &amp;ldquo;embedded&amp;rdquo; languages like SQL or regex, which normally are represented as just plain-old strings, μKanren takes more advantage of the host language&amp;rsquo;s features.
I recommend reading the original paper: it&amp;rsquo;s short, well-written, and easy to understand.
I did a write-up which you can read on Sourcehut.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD on a Raspberry Pi 4 with 4GB of RAM</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2020-12-23_freebsd_rpi4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 22:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2020-12-23_freebsd_rpi4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the story of how I managed to get FreeBSD running on a Raspberry Pi 4 with 4GB of RAM, though I think the setup story is pretty similar for those with 2GB and 8GB.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also managed to get Rust built from source, (kind of) which is nice because the default Rust installer doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work for FreeBSD running on a Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FreeBSD on a Raspberry Pi</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2020-02-12-freebsd-on-a-raspberry-pi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2020-02-12-freebsd-on-a-raspberry-pi/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a FreeBSD guy. My first computer was a FreeBSD machine that my dad had running in a closet. I learned how to use Emacs as well as the command line on that black-screen white-text no-mouse interface. That&amp;rsquo;s how real programmers spend their childhood! 😎 😜
I&amp;rsquo;ve only heard good things about FreeBSD. While not known as particularly desktop-friendly (various Linux distros win here) I&amp;rsquo;ve heard tales of its rock-solid stability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Citations with Pandoc</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2019-02-06-citations-with-pandoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 05:03:26 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2019-02-06-citations-with-pandoc/</guid>
      <description>Today I figured out how to get Pandoc to automatically generate MLA citations for me!
I used Pandoc and the Biblatex bibliography format. What&amp;rsquo;s nice about this is that you can enter in all the information you know about the source, keep it nice and organized in a file, and then change the citation style on the fly. Imagine if you thought you had to use MLA, but then realized you needed to switch to APA citation styles.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
