<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>school on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/school/</link>
    <description>Recent content in school on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/school/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reflections one year into a PhD program</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-08-05_one_year_into_phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-08-05_one_year_into_phd/</guid>
      <description>I started my PhD program about a year ago. In my first year I have:
Taken 4 &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; 3-credit-hour classes Participated in 3 seminars Switched advisors Attended 2 conferences (PLDI @ FCRC, JuliaCon) Presented my work at JuliaCon It&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of work, and there&amp;rsquo;s been a lot of stress. I&amp;rsquo;m in a much better place now than when I started, and over all I&amp;rsquo;m happy where I&amp;rsquo;m at and where I&amp;rsquo;m headed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Class Management Reviews: Fall 2021</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-12-18_classroom_management_reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-12-18_classroom_management_reviews/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A collection of what worked well and what didn&amp;rsquo;t in classes that I took this semester. This is partially for me to record what things reduced friction for me as a student so that one day, should I become a professor, I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to run the lowest-friction class ever!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Foundations of High-Modernist Ideology in Metropolis</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-12-07_metropolis_essay/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-12-07_metropolis_essay/</guid>
      <description>The following is from a essay from a class on German literature and film.
Fritz Lang’s movie Metropolis is primarily about the struggle between the oppressed working class and the ruling elite. What drives this tension, however, is a particular view of technology and technological progress that exacerbates the problems the film focuses on. This mentality is called high modernist ideology by Scott in his book Seeing Like a State:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using a Raspberry Pi for Proctorio</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-01-30_proctorio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2021 21:38:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2021-01-30_proctorio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For one of my classes I am required to take a short weekly exam via Proctorio. There&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/22/21526792/proctorio-online-test-proctoring-lawsuit-universities-students-coronavirus&#34;&gt;been some controversy&lt;/a&gt; surrounding this software. Although it claims it&amp;rsquo;s trustworthy, it&amp;rsquo;s not open-source, so no one can verify their claims. So naturally, I was reluctant to install it on my primary machine. Enter: the spare raspberry pi I have sitting around.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
