<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>academics on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/academics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in academics on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/academics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My promise to keep everything original</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-09-23_all_original/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-09-23_all_original/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a strange email the other day. Here it is, with parts redacted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is G&amp;mdash;, I am the main editor at &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While browsing your site, I noticed you have an amazing article from this page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Link to an extremely old post of mine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team actually just published a comprehensive article on &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Semi-related title&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; which I think your visitors would truly
appreciate and add value to your awesome article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check it out here: &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were willing to add our link to that page, I would be more than happy to share it to more than a thousand of our social followers to help you
gain some visibility in exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think and thank you for your consideration!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mail program correctly marked it as spam, which I appreciate. (Besides the spammy feel of the text, the article of mine they reference is an &amp;ldquo;amazing&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;300 word blurb about a one-day project I did in 2017. Sheesh…) I was a little shocked that someone would ask me to engage in the kind of social-metrics-engineering which I feel has contributed directly to many of the social problems plaguing us today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to make a public promise that I would hold myself to. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a scholar. As such, I have a sacred duty to uphold truth at all times and to share knowledge freely. I will never do anything that might compromise my ability to do such. If there is anything beautiful, truthful, or honorable, I will promote it. I will never accept bribery or engage in influence peddling; I find it intellectually and morally repugnant to use my station as an academic for personal gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll make mistakes—and I won&amp;rsquo;t stop talking about tools and services that I think genuinely serve my desires for greater knowledge, understanding, and freedom—but I will never do this in exchange for money, social clout, or whatever. If I attain any fame, it will not be because it was my end goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, G&amp;mdash;, here is what I think of your offer: &lt;em&gt;get lost—your proposal disgusts me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
