<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academics on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/academics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academics on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/academics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Skills That I Needed When I Started My PhD</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-07-09_phd_tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-07-09_phd_tools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting my third year as a PhD student. I thought it would be good to look back on some of the things that have helped me to this point. I study programming languages, but I imagine these things will help anyone in computer science&amp;mdash;and some might have application to other STEM fields as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;em&gt;many&lt;/em&gt; softer skills that you need as a PhD student: curiosity, good work ethic, organization, etc. These are essential and nothing can replace them. (Note: that was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an exhaustive list.) I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on some of the tools and hard skills that made the ride a little more comfortable. These compliment, rather than compete with, the softer skills that one develops as a beginning researcher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a rough list, and not a how-to article. This is mostly just a collection of things I&amp;rsquo;ve seen other people &lt;em&gt;lacking&lt;/em&gt; that have caused them to struggle. If you are considering doing a PhD, you might want to pick up some of these skills as you get ready to start to help you hit the ground running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;software-engineering&#34;&gt;
  Software engineering
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#software-engineering&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend reading &lt;em&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/em&gt; (Thomas, David and Hunt, Andrew, 2019). It&amp;rsquo;s written primarily for industry programmers, but there&amp;rsquo;s a lot in there that applies to anyone in CS research. All of the things I mention in this section are covered in detail in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;version-control&#34;&gt;
  Version Control
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#version-control&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have got to know Git. If you cannot wrangle versions of your software and papers (yes, put the papers you write under version control) you will waste much time shooting yourself in the foot and trying to recover work you lost. You will also be laughed to scorn should you ever depart academia for a stint in industry if you do not know Git.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all of the papers I have worked on, we have used Git to collaborate. We&amp;rsquo;ve typically used GitHub, which is fine as forges go, but I&amp;rsquo;ve also worked with a self-hosted GitLab instance, and that was fine too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;scripting&#34;&gt;
  Scripting
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#scripting&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is incredibly helpful to know a scripting language. I grew up on Perl, which makes munging large amounts of text a piece of cake. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to learn Perl; you should get really comfortable with a language that makes it easy to manipulate text and files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Makefiles are also super helpful. I like using Makefiles to simply give names to a particular workflow. A Makefile for building a paper might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#d8dee9;background-color:#2e3440;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-makefile&#34; data-lang=&#34;makefile&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#88c0d0&#34;&gt;paper.pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#81a1c1&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; paper.tex
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    latexmk -lualatex paper
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#88c0d0&#34;&gt;.PHONY&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#81a1c1&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; clean
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#88c0d0&#34;&gt;clean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#81a1c1&#34;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    @echo Cleanup &lt;span style=&#34;color:#81a1c1&#34;&gt;time&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    latexmk -c
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    rm -f paper.pdf
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, instead of remembering all the incantations necessary to do some task, I have given that task a &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; by which I can call it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;command-line&#34;&gt;
  Command line
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#command-line&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must become proficient with the command line. If you are doing research, you will likely need to run software that other researchers have produced. And more likely than not, this will be &lt;em&gt;rough&lt;/em&gt; software with bugs and sharp edges that is meant to demonstrate some research concept than be some practical tool ready for developers who only know how to code through YouTube videos and ChatGPT. That this software is rough is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://matt.might.net/articles/crapl/&#34;&gt;feature of research software&lt;/a&gt;, not a bug. &lt;strong&gt;There is &lt;em&gt;rarely&lt;/em&gt;, if ever, a GUI available.&lt;/strong&gt; You are going to have to do stuff on the command line, so get used to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting used to the command line helps with &lt;a href=&#34;#scripting&#34;&gt;Scripting&lt;/a&gt; as well. Any task you do on the command line, you can write a script to automate. Building little scripts to e.g. build your paper, your homework, your experiments, etc. will save you time in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;know-thy-editor&#34;&gt;
  Know thy editor
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#know-thy-editor&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs or Vim&amp;mdash;pick one and learn it &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well. VS Code is flashy and all, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the same depth and breadth of customizations that Emacs and Vim give you. Also, Emacs and Vim are free software. You are in control!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, of course, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/tags/emacs/&#34;&gt;love Emacs&lt;/a&gt; and I even made a &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/ashton314/emacs-bedrock&#34;&gt;starter kit called Bedrock&lt;/a&gt; to help some of my friends in my research lab get started with Emacs. I use Emacs to program, write papers, take notes, manage email, track tasks, and more. I made a list of &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-05-30_top_emacs_packages/&#34;&gt;my top Emacs packages&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks ago if you&amp;rsquo;d like more ideas on what is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vim is fine too and I will still respect you if you choose to go that route. ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;authoring-papers&#34;&gt;
  Authoring papers
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#authoring-papers&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;latex&#34;&gt;
  LaTeX
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#latex&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Familiarity with LaTeX has definitely helped me. Fighting with LaTeX is no fun, but you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; have to do a little bit of it at some point. Lots of people like using Overleaf; I prefer the command line. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong: Overleaf is awesome and makes collaborating in a Google Docs sort of way possible, but you loose some flexibility, and if something goes wrong on Overleaf right before your deadline, you&amp;rsquo;re toast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bibliographies&#34;&gt;
  Bibliographies
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#bibliographies&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lovely computer science bibliography hosted at &lt;a href=&#34;https://dblp.org/&#34;&gt;dblp.org&lt;/a&gt;. When I was going through the bibliography for &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-06-21_writing_a_paper/&#34;&gt;my last paper&lt;/a&gt; I was able to find lots of missing DOIs simply by putting in the title of the paper into the search bar; DBLP found all the bibliographic information that I needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;organization-and-communication&#34;&gt;
  Organization and communication
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#organization-and-communication&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;note-taking&#34;&gt;
  Note taking
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#note-taking&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take notes whenever you learn how to do something that wasn&amp;rsquo;t obvious to you when you started out doing it. I like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten&#34;&gt;Zettelkasten&lt;/a&gt; method for taking notes: whenever I learn how to e.g. do some complex layout in LaTeX or learn a neat Makefile trick, I write it down. You can think of it as writing your own personal &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; pages&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what a &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; page is, this is the standard manual system available on UNIX-like systems (e.g. FreeBSD, macOS, and Linux). Open a terminal and run &lt;code&gt;man man&lt;/code&gt; to read the manual page for &lt;code&gt;man&lt;/code&gt; itself. You really need to get comfortable with the &lt;a href=&#34;#command-line&#34;&gt;Command line&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these notes I rarely look back at. Others I revisit regularly. But even though I might not review some notes that frequently, there are cases where something on my system will break and a years-old note comes to my rescue from the &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; time I had to solve that problem. For example, I took notes on how to upgrade my language server for Elixir. I don&amp;rsquo;t upgrade that thing very often, but there is a little tweak I need to do just because of how my system is set up that is not obvious. It took me a few hours of debugging the first time, but, because I took notes, it now only takes me a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;email&#34;&gt;
  Email
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#email&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academics generally love email. It&amp;rsquo;s simple, robust, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t change its UI every few weeks, unlike &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; popular chat platforms. Unfortunately many universities are forcing everyone to move to Outlook. &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/posts/2022-08-28_keep_email_federated/&#34;&gt;This is a very bad thing.&lt;/a&gt; Fortunately, there are &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-05-03_email_with_outlook/&#34;&gt;some workarounds&lt;/a&gt; that you can use to reclaim some control over your email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a sweet workflow with my email. That&amp;rsquo;s right, I do it all from Emacs. Now, while I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; recommend you learn how to use Emacs, I understand that not everyone will start using Emacs. Everyone &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; get proficient with their email client and know how to use it well. I recommend anything that you can control entirely from the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should also get comfortable with editing replies. You know how, when you reply to an email, you usually see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some mail clients will make the &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; at the beginning of the line pretty with different colored lines and whatnot. It&amp;rsquo;s all angle brackets under the hood, and you can still edit it as described here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#d8dee9;background-color:#2e3440;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Hey here is my reply!
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;On Tuesday, 9 July 2024, Slartibartfast said:
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; Hey,
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; You were asking me where I found that elvish blade of great
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; antiquity. Turns out it was just sitting on a shelf in the living
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; room the whole time! I had the darndest time escaping the theif
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; though; I think he locked me into the cellar as soon as I went down
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; there. …
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just typing your reply above the email is called &amp;ldquo;top-posting&amp;rdquo;, and it&amp;rsquo;s considered bad form. You can actually edit the bit that was sent to interleave your reply with bits of the prior email. This makes it easier for people to know what you&amp;rsquo;re replying to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#d8dee9;background-color:#2e3440;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-text&#34; data-lang=&#34;text&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Hey Slarti
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; Turns out it was just sitting on a shelf in the living room the
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; whole time!
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;What!? No way! I must have missed it. I&amp;#39;ll grab it once I figure out
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;how to get up this chimney in the art studio.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; I had the darndest time escaping the theif though; I think he locked
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; me into the cellar as soon as I went down there.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Yeah, I cornered the guy in his hideout. I won the knife fight though.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When used appropriately, this makes emails much more pleasant to read. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t break the email thread either; you can still see the chain of replies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;task-tracking&#34;&gt;
  Task tracking
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#task-tracking&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need some way to keep track of tasks. I have a workflow based off of &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org/&#34;&gt;Org-mode&lt;/a&gt;, which I will not detail here. The short of it is that you need to be spending at least a little time with some regularity &amp;ldquo;sharpening the saw&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; by making sure that whatever tool you use to keep track of tasks is working for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;
  References
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#references&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas, David and Hunt, Andrew (2019). &lt;em&gt;The Pragmatic Programmer&lt;/em&gt;, Addison-Wesley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7_Habits_of_Highly_Effective_People&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_7_Habits_of_Highly_Effective_People&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons From Writing My First Academic Paper</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-06-21_writing_a_paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2024-06-21_writing_a_paper/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a paper published at &lt;a href=&#34;https://2024.ecoop.org/&#34;&gt;ECOOP&lt;/a&gt; this year! This is my first big paper published at a big conference. As such, I wanted to write down some things that I learned so that in the future I can remember a bit better what was hard for me. That way, should I one day advise PhD students working on &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; first papers, I can help them through the learning curve better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;marginnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For us, this artifact took the form of a Docker container with a bash script that ran all the code examples from our paper to support the claims we made. I really like that reproducibility like this is often an option in CS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Conference deadlines may be flexible if you talk to the right people.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;We submitted an artifact along with our paper But some of the deadlines were &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; close. My advisor reached out to the folks in charge of the conference&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and asked if the artifact submission date could be moved back. The organizers agreed, and everyone got a little more breathing room between when the paper was due and when the artifact was supposed to be submitted.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Conferences are run by humans—you can talk to them.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Along the same lines, the conferences are run by &lt;em&gt;people&lt;/em&gt;, and you can talk to the organizers to request clarification. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a whiny jerk, of course, but the people running these things &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; people to submit good papers and will work to help you overcome blockers.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;The Call for Papers has everything you need.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Call for Papers&amp;rdquo; describes what kinds of submissions fit the conference, as well as &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to format and submit your paper. You can see the CfP for ECOOP &lt;a href=&#34;https://2024.ecoop.org/track/ecoop-2024-papers#Call-for-Papers&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Absorbing everything in the CfP can be challenging for first-timers. I was unclear about something and my advisor asked me if I had read the CfP. I had, but that didn&amp;rsquo;t mean that I remembered &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; from it. It takes time and experience to absorb the salient parts of the CfP.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Papers get easier to read as time goes on.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;When I first started research, I struggled to make it through a single paper. Moreover, I had a hard time understanding the point the paper was trying to make.
&lt;p&gt;I think part of the difficulty stems from the sheer amount of new terminology and dense technical material present in a typical paper. Everything is new and therefore requires effort to comprehend. As you get familiar with the field, however, previously arcane concepts become easy to grasp. This also makes it easier to see the main idea of the paper: you can tune out the noise and focus on what is novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of it comes from how unfamiliar the &lt;em&gt;form&lt;/em&gt; of papers is. When I started research, papers felt arbitrarily formulaic. Now, I can recognize common structures in papers and use these patterns to understand the paper quicker. I actually find that papers are an efficient way for me to learn about cutting-edge research. I hoped, but did not know, that that would eventually be the case when I started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Keep track of where &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; claim comes from.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I did not do a very good job keeping a lab notebook for this paper. When I started writing the paper, I had to go back to my work and try and remember where I got a particular number or why I made a particular claim. I am doing a lot better with my current project, I think. I hope the next paper is a little smoother in this regard.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Writing takes a long time!&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;We started working on this paper about 7 months ago, according to &lt;code&gt;git log&lt;/code&gt;. There were so many drafts, edits, and revisions.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Get your contributions clear.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Simon Peyton-Jones &lt;a href=&#34;https://simon.peytonjones.org/great-research-paper/&#34;&gt;gives this advice&lt;/a&gt;: your list of contributions should drive the paper. Moreover, writing the paper drives the research. Research is useless unless shared!&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Collaboration is challenging.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Writing joint papers can be tricky. I am really glad we were using &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; to track changes. I met with my advisor twice a week in person, as well as a few times remotely to hammer out the ideas and drafts in the paper. We sent lots of messages in Slack.
&lt;p&gt;Asking for feedback can be hard—and I don&amp;rsquo;t just mean in the emotional pride-bruising sense: prompting the people you ask for feedback can be tricky. I asked someone for some help on a different piece of writing, and they weren&amp;rsquo;t able to give me much useful help and instead focused on trivial issues. Part of that is on me: I should have prompted better. But it is hard to prompt well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it a little curious that different kinds of people have different affinities to methods of giving feedback. With this paper, there&amp;rsquo;s a flag in LaTeX that adds line numbers to the PDF. So, if someone wants to comment on something, they can write:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-nil&#34; data-lang=&#34;nil&#34;&gt;l 42: &amp;#34;that&amp;#34; → &amp;#34;which&amp;#34;; the phrase is not essential, so use &amp;#34;which&amp;#34; instead of &amp;#34;that&amp;#34;
l 46: &amp;#34;rocks are a kind of vegetable&amp;#34; do we have a citation for this?
…
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This seems natural to me. I like that it&amp;rsquo;s software-agnostic. I guess some fields are tied to particular technologies (e.g. suggested edits in Word) and that seems burdensome to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the program chair.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Commitment to Intellectual Integrity</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-09-23_all_original/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/2023-09-23_all_original/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a strange email the other day. Here it is, with parts redacted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is G&amp;mdash;, I am the main editor at &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While browsing your site, I noticed you have an amazing article from this page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Link to an extremely old post of mine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team actually just published a comprehensive article on &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Semi-related title&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; which I think your visitors would truly
appreciate and add value to your awesome article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check it out here: &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you were willing to add our link to that page, I would be more than happy to share it to more than a thousand of our social followers to help you
gain some visibility in exchange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think and thank you for your consideration!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G&amp;mdash; &amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&amp;mdash;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mail program correctly marked it as spam, which I appreciate. (Besides the spammy feel of the text, the article of mine they reference is an &amp;ldquo;amazing&amp;rdquo; &amp;gt;300 word blurb about a one-day project I did in 2017. Sheesh…) I was a little shocked that someone would ask me to engage in the kind of social-metrics-engineering which I feel has contributed directly to many of the social problems plaguing us today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to make a public promise that I would hold myself to. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;info&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a scholar. As such, I have a sacred duty to uphold truth at all times and to share knowledge freely. I will never do anything that might compromise my ability to do such. If there is anything beautiful, truthful, or honorable, I will promote it. I will never accept bribery or engage in influence peddling; I find it intellectually and morally repugnant to use my station as an academic for personal gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll make mistakes—and I won&amp;rsquo;t stop talking about tools and services that I think genuinely serve my desires for greater knowledge, understanding, and freedom—but I will never do this in exchange for money, social clout, or whatever. If I attain any fame, it will not be because it was my end goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, G&amp;mdash;, here is what I think of your offer: &lt;em&gt;get lost—your proposal disgusts me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
