<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Docs on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/docs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Docs on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/docs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/docs/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/docs/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-me&#34;&gt;
  About Me
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#about-me&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Ashton Wiersdorf, and I&amp;rsquo;m a PhD student at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://utah.edu/&#34;&gt;University of Utah&lt;/a&gt; studying programming languages with &lt;a href=&#34;https://cs.brown.edu/people/bgreenma/&#34;&gt;Ben Greenman&lt;/a&gt;. I live in Salt Lake City, Utah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My most recent place of employment outside of academia was with &lt;a href=&#34;https://spiff.com/&#34;&gt;Spiff&lt;/a&gt;, where they were nice enough to let me hack on their interpreter. Before Spiff I worked at a few other positions as a full-stack engineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve sung with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choirs_at_Brigham_Young_University&#34;&gt;BYU Men&amp;rsquo;s Chorus&lt;/a&gt; and I play the piano. Other hobbies include swimming and hiking&amp;mdash;Utah has some of the most diverse landscape anywhere in the US: from dense forests to barren desert. If you visit, I highly recommend checking out some of the national parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/img/me_and_sarah.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been married to my wife Sarah since 2018; we met when we were in high school and she&amp;rsquo;s been my best friend ever since. You can see her blog &lt;a href=&#34;https://sarah.wiersdorf.org/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. We became parents in the summer of 2021 and couldn&amp;rsquo;t be happier!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I served a two-year mission for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://churchofjesuschrist.org&#34;&gt;Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints&lt;/a&gt; in Germany. Consequently, I speak fluent German and have a great appetite for German food. My wife and I were able to visit Berlin for a few months in 2019. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in visiting Europe, Berlin is a must.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is primarily where I&amp;rsquo;ll post about research, school, and programming. I&amp;rsquo;m studying programming languages, though my interests are not strictly constrained to any one field. I like literature and philosophy, so there will be the occasional book review that I&amp;rsquo;ll post under my &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/&#34;&gt;personal section&lt;/a&gt;. I change my mind a lot; I&amp;rsquo;m still learning, so things written here should not be understood as an immutable reflection of my opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;colophon&#34;&gt;
  Colophon
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#colophon&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is built by &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, and the theme is &lt;a href=&#34;https://themes.gohugo.io/themes/hugo-book/&#34;&gt;hugo-book&lt;/a&gt;. The main font is &lt;a href=&#34;https://practicaltypography.com/charter.html&#34;&gt;Charter&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s hosted on &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For analytics I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goatcounter.com/&#34;&gt;Goat Counter&lt;/a&gt; which doesn&amp;rsquo;t track any personal data. It&amp;rsquo;s basically just a way for me to see what&amp;rsquo;s popular and what&amp;rsquo;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time I write my blog in &lt;a href=&#34;https://emacs.org&#34;&gt;Emacs&lt;/a&gt;. I use &lt;a href=&#34;https://ox-hugo.scripter.co/&#34;&gt;ox-hugo&lt;/a&gt; to export from org-mode to Hugo-friendly Markdown. I used to use the built-in org-mode export, but it messed things up like apostrophes and didn&amp;rsquo;t handle some other formatting as I wanted it to. ox-hugo does a much better job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the third iteration of my blog style. Previously I&amp;rsquo;ve run blogs with Ghost and Jekyll. I moved to Jekyll from Ghost because I wanted a lighter-weight static site, and I moved from Jekyll to Hugo for the lovely themes and some of the more advanced capabilities it offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://emacs.org/&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/img/made_with_emacs.svg&#34; style=&#34;height: 3rem&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
