<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>faith on Lambda Land</title>
    <link>https://lambdaland.org/tags/faith/</link>
    <description>Recent content in faith on Lambda Land</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://lambdaland.org/tags/faith/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Christmas 2021</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-12-25_christmas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-12-25_christmas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my first Christmas being a dad. The end of the school semester was unusually stressful; I didn&amp;rsquo;t have much time or energy to anticipate Christmas. But I&amp;rsquo;ve felt a marked lack of eagerness for &lt;em&gt;getting&lt;/em&gt; presents. That feeling wanes each year—something I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for—but this year I only felt an eagerness for a time of peace and celebration with my family. Peaceful it has been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My family isn&amp;rsquo;t perfect. (My baby daughter is about as perfect as they come, though!) The time I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten to spend so far and the time that I will spend with them is precious to me. My wife and I have focused so much on celebrating the birth of Jesus Christ that this commercialized junk we put up with has been all but absent from our home. We have a few books about Santa Claus that we read to our daughter, but we&amp;rsquo;ve listened to strictly Christ-centered music. (&lt;em&gt;A Charlie Brown Christmas&lt;/em&gt; counts, though!) There&amp;rsquo;s been a spirit in our home that has brought me comfort and peace in this tumultuous year—more than any before it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas—may the peace of God be with you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This Too Shall Pass</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-06-13_this_shall_pass/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-06-13_this_shall_pass/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s cliché at this point to say that 2020 was a rough year. I&amp;rsquo;m grateful in that I and my wife were relatively unscathed by the pandemic. I had some personal health issues however that by themselves made 2020 a bit of a struggle. I learned some important lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In February I had a big choir concert. That same weekend I had a large project for one of my CS classes due. I got an extension on my CS project so I could sing in the concert; but despite the extension, I was rushed and I spent an unusually long time in front of my computer working on my project after the concert was over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the nature of the project, I had to use a mouse for much of it. The strain of pronation&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; for such a long time did something in my right forearm. The next day I felt an ache every time I tried to turn my hands downward: even with a 15° tent on my split keyboard, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t lay my hands down to type. I felt a burning along the inside of my forearm whenever I tried. My grip was shot as well: I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to open any tight jars, and I had to use my left hand for a lot of things that I normally would use my right hand for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, at age 23, had developed a repetitive-strain injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went to a physical therapist. An ultrasound revealed no issues with my nerves. I was really happy about that because it meant that I didn&amp;rsquo;t need surgery. But I did need some non-surgical intervention: after many weeks of rest from work and several visits to a physical therapist, my hand started feeling a little better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a month or so I was able to start going back to work. I started at working a few hours here and there, and over the course of a few months scaled back up to something close to what my hours normally were. I was extra-vigilant in doing my stretches and exercises that I had gotten from the physical therapist. Things were looking up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it started hurting again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn&amp;rsquo;t take much: just a small deviation from my workout and a little added stress on my hands sent me back to the doctor. Some more deep-muscle massages and another break from work helped me to get back on track. But I was feeling shaken and a little depressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cycle happened again a few more times. Each time, I wondered if I would ever be back to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; when I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to worry so much about my hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had been on the mend for a while and was feeling pretty happy about where I was. I invested in a new split keyboard that had more buttons for my thumbs which took the strain off of my pinky fingers. I switched to Vim-bindings in Emacs&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and made a concerted effort to avoid the mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I started running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found a trail close by to where I live: it&amp;rsquo;s shady and pretty level. Running had always been my &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; favorite form of exercise, but I discovered that I actually &lt;em&gt;enjoyed&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After just a few days, I noticed that my hands were feeling better than they ever had before. I think the cardio helped my hands get some more blood that they had been missing. My hands still feel great. Some days I don&amp;rsquo;t think about the fact that they were injured, which is a miracle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, after my first 5k, I got a bad case of runner&amp;rsquo;s knee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still feeling it. It&amp;rsquo;s been a few days, and even walking has been has been a little painful. I think I pushed it too hard too quickly. I&amp;rsquo;m not great at this physical training thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve lost (temporarily) the form of exercise that I was &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; starting to enjoy. But something that I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from cycles of health and injury is that bad times come… and they also go. In the case of my hands, it took well over a year for me to feel like I was in a more normal place. I still feel like I&amp;rsquo;m on the mend—I still have a hard time using the keyboard on my laptop—but I&amp;rsquo;m optimistic that &lt;em&gt;this time&lt;/em&gt; the worst is behind me, at least for the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still young, and I&amp;rsquo;m only just getting used to the idea that injuries don&amp;rsquo;t heal as well as they do when you&amp;rsquo;re a kid. It&amp;rsquo;s been a bit of a struggle to come to grips with that idea, but I&amp;rsquo;m getting there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s always the best of times, as well as the worst of times. I&amp;rsquo;ve watched my wife, parents, and friends go through similar seasons of difficulty—sometimes spanning years of distress—only to emerge triumphant in some cases, or adapt when the difficulties never pass fully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe there is hope. I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for my family and my faith which helped carry me though these hard times. I know more will come, but I know I will make it through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motion of turning the palm downwards. Opposite of supination, which is to turn the palm upwards.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, Vim-bindings! That&amp;rsquo;s a post for another day. I started using &lt;a href=&#34;https://evil.readthedocs.io/en/latest/overview.html&#34;&gt;evil-mode&lt;/a&gt; and I can now say that the best text-editor is Emacs with Vim-bindings enabled.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Easter 2021</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-03-21_easter_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2021-03-21_easter_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love Easter. In my mind it is just as important as Christmas. Indeed, if Christ had not died for our sins and been resurrected, then there would be no reason to celebrate His birth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recorded a short, simple vocal arrangement of &amp;ldquo;O Savior, Thou Who Wearest a Crown&amp;rdquo; by J. S. Bach with my wife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Recording of &#34;O Savior, Thou Who Wearest a Crown&#34;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;audio
        controls
        src=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/etc/o_savior.mp3&#34;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element. Download it &lt;a href=&#34;https://lambdaland.org/etc/o_savior.mp3&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m no audio engineer, but I tried to make it fun to listen to with headphones. :) Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Best Two Years</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-11-20-the-best-two-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 06:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-11-20-the-best-two-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;September 30th marked two years since I arrived home from serving a two-year mission for the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints. The mission is colloquially referred to as &amp;ldquo;the best two years&amp;rdquo;. (There is &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Best_Two_Years&#34;&gt;a movie about missionaries&lt;/a&gt;, which I have not seen, by this title.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My time on the mission did constitute the best two years of my life. I grew and learned so much in that time. Not only did I get to visit some incredible historical places (I visited the Berlin Wall, a concentration camp, and Karl Friedrich Gauss&amp;rsquo;s grave, just to name a few) but I got to get to know people from all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also thought about the meaning of life and the nature of joy every day. Focusing on helping other people be happy has a profound effect on one&amp;rsquo;s own happiness—I forgot myself, my worries, and my cares, and found joy in helping others learn more about Jesus Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-past-two-years&#34;&gt;
  The past two years
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#the-past-two-years&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I left on my mission, my dad wrote the following to me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These will be the best two years of your life &lt;em&gt;until this point&lt;/em&gt;. When you return home, continue to serve the Lord, and those will be the best to years of your life after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been true for me. Since returning home, I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to start school, serve in multiple callings, be a home teacher, visit China, find some long-lost family members in Germany, help friends through some bouts of depression, and marry a most wonderful woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life has been awesome. Sure, there have been hard times. My life is far from perfect. I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten ill, been stressed, felt sorrow at the pain my friends and family went through at times. I&amp;rsquo;ve grown from these things, however. I&amp;rsquo;ve found meaning in continuing to serve God in my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; life. It&amp;rsquo;s been wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;God is good. He loves us, and wants the best for us. It might not always seem like it, but if we see hard times and growing pains, He will take us to places we never dreamt were possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;die-beste-zwei-jahren&#34;&gt;
  Die Beste zwei Jahren
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#die-beste-zwei-jahren&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am 30. September ist es zwei Jahren gewesen, seitdem ich von ein zwei jährige ehrenamtlich Mission für die Kirche Jesu Christi der Heiligen der letzten Tagen heimgekehrt bin. Die Mission wird umgangssprachlich als &amp;ldquo;die beste zwei Jahren&amp;rdquo; genannt. (Es gibt sogar einen Film, den ich nicht angeschaut habe, der so genannt ist.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meine Mission war die beste zwei Jahren meines Lebens. Ich habe viel gelernt. Ich habe auch viele tolle historische Orten besucht, wie z.B. die Berliner Mauer, einen Konzentrationslager, und den Grab von Karl Friedrich Gauss. Es gibt auch Menschen aus ganz vielen Ländern in Deutschland und es war schön so viele Menschen kennenzulernen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ich habe auch täglich an den Sinn des Lebens und die Natur von Freude. Wenn man sich auf die Freude von andern konzentriert, wird man selbst Glücklich. Ich habe mich selbst vergessen und andern geholfen von Christus zu erfahren, und dadurch habe ich Freude gefunden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;die-letzte-zwei-jahren&#34;&gt;
  Die letzte zwei Jahren
  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#die-letzte-zwei-jahren&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Als ich bereit war nach Deutschland zu fliegen, hat mein Vater mir folgendes geschrieben:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Die nächste zwei Jahren werden die besten so weit sein. Nachdem du nach Hause kommst, diene den Herr weiter und du wirst immer weiter die &amp;ldquo;beste zwei Jahren&amp;rdquo; erfahren.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das stimmt. Seitdem ich zurückgekehrt bin, habe ich mit der Schule angefangen, viel Dienst in und aus der Kirche geleistet, China besucht, Familienmitglieder aus Deutschland gefunden und eine wunderbare Frau heiraten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Das Leben ist ausgezeichnet. Es ist zwar schwierig ab und zu: ich habe mich erkältet, Stress erlebt, usw. Jedoch, ich bin ein besseres Mensch dank diese Schwierigkeiten. Ich bin dankbar, dass ich Gott noch als ein &amp;ldquo;normaler&amp;rdquo; Mensch dienen darf. Es ist einfach wunderbar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gott ist gut. Er liebt uns und er will, dass wir Freude finden. Es kann sein, dass es nicht immer so scheint, aber wenn wir unsere Prüfungen als Wachstumsschmerzen betrachten, wird Gott uns bessere Menschen machen—besser als was wir uns vorstellen könnten.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Light</title>
      <link>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-02-19-light/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2018 22:58:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://lambdaland.org/posts/personal/2018-02-19-light/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across a quote posted by a friend of mine that read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between spiritualism and religion is that spiritualism is pro-light, while religion is anti-sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or something to that effect. This quote bothered me because I felt that it maligned religion. I asked this friend for some clarification; it seemed clear from their response that they had had a rather negative experience with religion. They explained that they felt that religion (in general) micro-manages the lives of its adherents and focuses on telling people what they can&amp;rsquo;t do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to know everything about what my friend has experienced. To be sure, there is no perfectly lived religion on earth. I can understand to some degree where negative sentiments about religion come from. However, I am happy to report that my experience with religion has been a profoundly positive one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came across the following in the Book of Mormon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And whatsoever thing persuadeth men to do good is of me; for good cometh of none save it be of me. I am the same that leadeth men to all good…&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lds.org/scriptures/bofm/ether/4.12&#34;&gt;Ether 4:12&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My religion is very much &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; about what one can and cannot do. Rather, my religion is about living to &lt;em&gt;maximize joy&lt;/em&gt;. All those things that we are told not to do are things that, in the long run, will bring sadness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I would like to note that by &lt;em&gt;joy&lt;/em&gt;, I mean something distinct from &lt;em&gt;pleasure&lt;/em&gt;. Pleasure is a transient, ephemeral sensation, whereas joy is a deep, pure, lasting happiness.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I try to focus on what I &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do to bring more happiness to myself and those around me. Often, that means trying to find people to serve. There&amp;rsquo;s a quote that I like from a video about service called &lt;em&gt;Lift&lt;/em&gt;. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t watched it, it&amp;rsquo;s only a few minutes long and well worth it. You can watch it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.lds.org/media-library/video/2015-05-003-lift?lang=eng#p3s:436040&amp;amp;p3e:468150&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting, the dichotomy between healing the body and healing the soul. When we heal the body, it&amp;rsquo;s always an inward effort. We&amp;rsquo;re always paying attention to ourselves. When we heal the soul, turning inward doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. And the triage of the soul is found in turning outward to other people.&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;Lift&lt;/em&gt; at ~7&#39;14&amp;quot;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for my faith because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t restrict me from things I want to do or coerce me into doing things I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do. It has taught me to tame my naturally destructive tendencies and to nurture my good impulses. It has made me happier, and has given me peace and direction in my life. I am a better person because of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photo credit: Photo by Marcus Dall Col on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
